前情提要
Previously on Foundation…
我将与哈里谢顿共事
I'm going to work with Hari Seldon.
你熟悉我在心理历史学方面的研究
Are you familiar with my work? Psychohistory?
谢顿和那女孩 在动用武力上不用顾虑太多
Seldon and the girl. Don't overthink the stick.
银河帝国将在五个世纪内化为废墟
The Galactic Empire will lie in ruins within five centuries.
我们将受到一次又一次大事件的冲击
This mass of events rushing to meet us.
大帝决定
The Emperor has determined
允许你们在端点星建造你们的基地
you will be allowed to build your Foundation on Terminus.
你要流放我们
You're exiling us.
（改编自艾萨克阿西莫夫的小说）
（矮行星艾斯拉）
糟糕
Shit.
（注意 发现入侵者）
（删除数据）
（清除数据）
吉安克佛 你的颈椎已受伤
Jiam Quarver, you have suffered a cervical spinal cord injury.
除非我们介入 否则你很快将窒息
In a few moments you will suffocate, unless we intervene.
我们知道你在运作这个非法生物入侵设施
We know you operate this illicit biohacking facility.
我们也知道你制造了两个皮下纳米炸弹
We also know you manufactured the two subcutaneous nano-lace explosives
即炸毁星桥的袭击者所用的炸弹
used by the bombers who destroyed the Star Bridge.
但我们不知道的是
Now, what we don't know is the identity of the people
是谁与你的实验室签合约完成这项工作
who contracted with your lab to have this work done.
我同伴所使用的设备将刺激你的膈神经
The device my associate is applying will stimulate your phrenic nerves
让你能再次呼吸
and allow you to breathe again.
你接下来所说的话将决定 我们是否继续让这个设备运行
The next words you utter will determine if that device remains functioning.
谁是炸弹的买家
So, who purchased the bombs?
我们已经审问了数千名嫌疑人
We've questioned thousands of persons of interest,
但是炸弹生产者
but the chain of intermediaries linking the bomb maker
和袭击的真正幕后主导 之间的联系链无法追踪
to the attack's true authors has proven intractable.
还有多少尸体仍在沿川陀的轨道绕行
How many bodies are still orbiting Trantor?
十二万七千具 大帝
127,000, Empire.
为什么还没收回尸体
Why haven't they been retrieved?
那不是目前最优先的任务 救援和修复才是…
It hasn't been the highest priority. Rescue and recovery have--
让它成为最优先的任务
Make it a priority.
尸体在再次进入大气层时会燃烧
The corpses have been catching fire as they reenter the atmosphere.
人们只要一抬头就能想起我们有多无能
All anyone has to do is look up to be reminded of our impotence.
我们需要看到实际成果
We need results.
我们需要确定性 兄弟
We need certainty, Brother.
我会为流放谢顿和他的信徒感到后悔吗
Am I going to regret exiling Seldon and his followers?
没有证据表明他们与袭击有关
No evidence links them to the attack.
没有证据表明他们无罪
No evidence exonerates them.
我仍然可以让他们毁灭 即使相隔这么远也可以
I could destroy them still, even at a distance.
我们可以说是他们做的
We could say they did it.
可以让所有新闻渠道全天报道
Every source of news could say it every hour on the hour
直到这条消息无处不在 不留任何容人质疑的空间
until the air is made of that and there's nothing else to breathe.
杀害异见人士是一种冒险的做法
Martyring dissidents is a risky enterprise.
让你的大帝感到不爽也很冒险
So is annoying your emperor.
86981597
86,981,597.
86981689
86,981,689.
86981717
86,981,717.
86981729
86,981,729.
猜到你在这里
Figured I'd find you here.
抱歉
Sorry.
不是故意吵醒你的
Didn't mean to wake you.
-你睡觉时在数质数 -我数到多少了
-You were counting primes in your sleep. -How far did I get?
很遗憾地告诉你 没数到最后的一个
Not the end, if that's what you're hoping for.
-最后一个并不存在 -你说的是数字还是麻烦
-There is no end. -Numbers or problems to count?
我们不需要把整个星球变为殖民地 盖尔
We don't have to colonize the whole planet, Gaal.
只拥有属于自己的小角落就够了
Just our own tiny corner.
球体是没有角的
There are no corners on a sphere.
你要上来吗
You coming out?
不 你下来
No. Come in.
你知道我不会游泳
You know I can't swim.
你有四年又四个月的时间用来学
You've got four years and four months to learn.
想都别想
Not a chance.
别紧张…有我在
Relax, relax, relax. I've got you.
对不起…
I'm sorry. I'm sorry.
这个表现是不可接受的
Performance was unacceptable…
蓝队表现得一塌糊涂
Blue Team's tanking.
我的建议是到时候一定跟红队或绿队飞
When the time comes, fly Red or Green is my hint to you.
也许下一个训练期我可以加入反应器组
Maybe I'll join the reactor group next training period.
昨天晚餐的汤有点凉
Hmm, soup was a little cold at dinner last night.
也许你也打算去餐饮组训练几周
Maybe you wanna do a couple of weeks in culinary as well?
我懂你的意思
I understand your point--
你不需要学做殖民地的每一份工作 盖尔
You don't have to learn every job in the colony, Gaal.
如果他们做不好 那就需要
Well, I do if they can't do them.
距离在端点星着陆还有54个月
We have, what, 54 more months until we land on Terminus.
我们有时间 多的是时间
We have time. A lot of time.
对 可惜光阴似箭 说没就没
Well, we do until we don't.
抱歉 我不应该这样浪费宝贵的时间
Sorry. I shouldn't be wasting our dwindling time like that.
你能不能别这么认真地对待我的话
When will you stop taking me so seriously?
雪芳 我侦测到那边有高浓度的汞和砷
Shivaughn, I'm picking up high levels of mercury and arsenic there.
多加小心
Just be careful.
尽量快速地堵住那条裂缝 那里有毒
Try and seal that seam quickly. It's toxic.
我在堵了
I'm on it.
有人吗
Hello?
该死
Shit.
雪芳 快跑
Run, Shivaughn!
糟了 趴下
Shit! Stay down.
不 阿巴斯
No, Abbas!
恭喜 你们三次都全军覆没
Congratulations, you guys are zero for three.
盖尔、雪芳 因为你们位于主要爆破半径内
Because you were in the primary blast radius, Gaal and Shivaughn,
你们两人的中空器官都承受过大压力
both of you suffered from overpressure to your hollow organs.
我估计绞尽脑汁也想不到 比这更痛苦的死亡方式了
I could try, but I doubt I could find a more painful way to die.
马莉、布里恩、阿巴斯
Mari, Briwan, Abbas.
你们全都死于炸裂的岩石碎片
You were all killed by exploded rock fragments.
好消息是当场死去
The good news, it was instant.
坏消息是你们没活下来
The bad news, you're still dead.
总比被那东西撕裂要好
Better than that thing tearing us apart.
对 那到底是什么
Yeah, what the hell was that?
主教爪 外围星域特有的本地巨型动物
A bishop's claw. Local megafauna, endemic to the Outer Reach.
但阿巴斯说得对 模拟器并不公平
But Abbas is right. The sim's unfair.
就算他没开火 主教爪估计也会要了我们所有人的命
If he hadn't fired, the bishop's claw would've probably killed us all anyway.
对 确实不公平
Yes, it is unfair.
端点星上的一切都不公平
Everything about Terminus is unfair.
但若希望基地成功 我们必须克服这些困难
But we need to defy those odds if the Foundation is to succeed.
明天早上6点再试一次
We'll try again at 0600 tomorrow.
多尼克女士 谢顿博士想见你
Ms. Dornick, Dr. Seldon wants to see you.
帝国花园中有一个苹果园
There's an apple orchard in the Imperial Gardens
园子在机器人战争之前就存在了
that's older than the Robot Wars.
他们过去会在那里 对人工智能支持者处以绞刑
They used to hang AI sympathizers there.
我不知道以前有人工智能支持者
I didn't know there were robot sympathizers.
支持者一直都有
There are always sympathizers.
希望在这次旅程结束时
Well, hopefully, by the end of this trip,
这棵树的树枝已经足够粗壮 可以吊死人了
this one will be strong enough to hang somebody.
希望吧
Hopefully.
你处理熔岩管时遇到问题了
You had trouble with the lava tube.
熔岩管永远都有问题
We always have trouble with the lava tube.
你的解决方案是什么
What's your solution?
别把基地安置在熔岩管附近
Don't settle the Foundation near the lava tube.
需要熔岩管获取能源
We need it for energy production.
我们需要人钻井获取地热能源
We need people to drill wells for geothermal energy.
如果矿层不稳定 总是燃烧 我们就无法这么做
And we won't have any if unstable veins keep igniting.
-是苦的 -但至少是活的
-It's bitter. -But alive.
你用今早的模拟数据进行发展预测了吗
Have you run thrive projections using this morning's sim data?
-是的 -包括蓝队的失败
-Yeah. -Including Blue Team's catastrophe?
着陆五年后 死亡率为34.2%
34.2% mortality after five years' planetfall.
呈下降趋势 情况乐观
Trending downwards. Optimism abounds.
把这点告诉船上的1710个人…
Tell that to the 1,710 people on--
这就是我们进行模拟测试的原因 盖尔
That's the reason we run sims, Gaal.
-早上好 哈里 -早上好 马格纳斯
-Morning, Hari. -Morning, Magnus.
“哈里”
"Hari."
旅程开始时 人们都叫我“谢顿博士”
I was "Dr. Seldon" when we began this journey.
这真的是坏事吗
Is that really such a bad thing?
让他们了解数学以外的你
For them to know the man behind the math?
一会儿有个基地预算分配会议
There's a Foundation budget allocation conference later.
-你得代我参加 -我从没去…
-I need you to sit in for me. -I've never gone--
不过是些数字 盖尔
It's just numbers, Gaal.
不过是数字
It's just numbers.
是
Yeah.
数学从来就不只是数字
Math is never just numbers.
当语言失效 我们用数学描述那些无法表达的东西
When words fail us, we use math to describe the inexpressible.
最让我们恐惧的东西
The things that terrify us most.
太空的广袤
The vastness of space,
时间的形态
the shape of time…
人类灵魂的重量和价值
the weight and worth of a human soul.
这是一首古老的 安纳克里昂狩猎歌 对吗
That's an old Anacreon hunting song, isn't it?
在猎杀动物之前唱的
You invoke it before you kill the animal.
对吗
Yes?
任何人都可能唱这首歌 大帝
Anyone could sing that, Emperor.
那不是真的
That's not true.
我们试图把唱你的歌作为教育的一部分
We've tried to sing your songs as part of our education.
但就是无法像本地人一样掌握你们的方言
Never mastered the dialect. Not like a native.
但听起来完美无缺 不是吗
But it sounds perfect, doesn't it?
正如我们在过去两周所表示的
As we have for the last two weeks,
安纳克里昂坚决否认参与这一次…
Anacreon firmly denies any involvement in this--
我不知该用哪个词
I cannot find words for it.
正确的用词是摧毁星桥
The words are the destruction of the Star Bridge
造成一亿川陀居民的死亡
and the deaths of 100 million citizens of Trantor.
这是狄斯比斯语 对吗
That was Thespin, wasn't it?
你能翻译一下吗
Can you translate?
大声点
Louder!
意思是“外围星域万岁”
It means, "Long live the Outer Reach."
我猜你也能听得出狄斯比斯语的祷告词
I assume you can also recognize the Thespin prayer heard
就在炸弹将环形平台从索道上炸断之前 有人念诵这句话
right before bombs ripped the orbital platform from the stalk.
恕我无礼 大帝 那祷告词…
With all due respect, Empire, that prayer--
已经88年没被念诵过了
Hasn't been sung in 88 years.
没有哪个狄斯比斯人会念诵…
No Thespin would sing--
我们星球的政府仍然否认…
My government continues to deny--
罩住他们
Shroud them.
录下的影像是真实的 他们不知道真相
What's on the recording is authentic. They don't have answers.
总有人知道
Someone does.
这两个世界互相憎恨
These worlds hate each other.
-超越他们对帝国的憎恨  -历史上的确如此
-More than they hate the Empire? -Historically, yes.
他们在这件事上合作实在是…
The idea they'd collaborate on such a thing…
但是…
And yet…
会有人为此事上绞架的
someone's going to hang for this.
我希望是有罪的那个
I'd like it to be the guilty one.
黄昏兄弟去哪了
Where is Brother Dusk?
好了 谢谢 盖尔
Okay. Thanks, Gaal.
受精卵的状况不错
Zygote looks good.
你的生育指示有什么变动吗
Any change in your birth directive?
没有
No.
人们会和我说自己的事
People talk to me.
-肯定的 -不只是这里 在外面也是
-I'm sure. -Well, not just here, but out there.
因为不是所有人都想等到着陆的那天
'Cause not everyone wants to wait for planetfall.
那不奇怪
That's not surprising.
要是我知道有人…
If I knew someone--
她还在妊娠早期
She's still early-term.
她仍然可以按照规程行事 但她不愿过来
She could still follow protocol, but she won't come in.
我应该告诉谢顿博士吗  还是只需要告诉你
Do I need to tell Dr. Seldon? Or is it enough just to tell you?
一切可好
Everything check out okay?
一切都很好
Everything's fine.
一会儿见
Find you later?
好的
Okay.
注意 五号象限区清理完毕 现可使用
Attention. Quadrant five is now clear.
五号象限区清理完毕 现可使用
Quadrant five, all clear.
告诉谢顿博士 今晚我们会再进行一次反应器模拟
Tell Dr. Seldon we're running an extra reactor sim tonight.
希望这次不会 让三架穿梭机都暴露在辐射下
Hopefully we won't radiate all three shuttles this time.
我不是为了这个来找你的
I'm not here about that.
孩子的父亲知道吗
Does the father know?
我们几乎是陌生人
We barely know each other.
他看起来人不错 但我不在乎他的想法
He seems sweet, but I don't care much what he thinks.
有谁的想法是你在乎的吗
Do you care what anyone thinks?
有 所以我才会告诉种子库的雪芳
Enough to talk to Shivaughn at the seed bank.
但很显然 那不明智
Look where that got me.
我不是代表基地来和你聊的
I'm not talking to you as the Foundation.
我是以盖尔的身份和你聊
I'm talking to you as Gaal.
劳莉 你是一位工程师
Lowre, you're an engineer.
你通过测试加入了穿梭机团队
You tested onto the shuttle team.
你知道胚胎放在种子库要安全得多
You know how much safer an embryo is in the seed bank.
这艘飞船不是为了孕妇而设计的
This ship wasn't designed for pregnancy.
难道端点星就是
And Terminus is?
我并不傻
I'm not stupid.
我知道这里的辐射水平多高
I know how much radiation we're getting hit with up here.
我清楚整个孕期保持健康的概率 出生缺陷的概率
I know the odds of carrying healthy to term, and defects,
和母乳被污染的概率
and my milk being poison.
但我也很清楚目的地的状况
But I also know where we're going.
冰岩、长夜、没有遮风挡雨的植被
Frozen rock, long nights, no trees for shelter.
我知道你们预测了我们的死亡人数
I know you've got projections of how many of us are going to die,
而大家都不愿承认那个数字有多大
and that the number is higher than anyone wants to admit.
-劳莉 不是这样的 -没有人想说…
-Lowre, that's not true. -No one wants to tell--
别骗我了
Don't lie to me!
哈里谢顿对我说谎也就罢了 那是我意料之中的 但你不行
It's okay for Hari Seldon to lie to me. I expect that, but not from you.
请把真相告诉我
Please just tell me the truth.
这样我才知道 这是你的话 而不是他的话
That's how I know it's you talking and not him.
我知道做什么是对的 盖尔 我明白
I know what the right thing to do is, Gaal. I know.
我知道计算的概率
I know what the math is.
我知道我们在这飞船上的日子 不算真正的生活
I know that what we're doing on this ship isn't really living.
我们只是在为生存做准备
We're just preparing to live.
为我们中一些人的生存做准备
For some of us to live.
这是计划的一部分
It's the Plan.
如果我让他们取出她后出了事
What if I let them take her out and something happens,
然后我再也无法感受她在我体内生长呢
and I never get to feel her grow inside me ever again?
我将永远无法看着她的眼睛
I'll just never get to look into her eyes.
没什么比这更糟糕的事了
There would be nothing worse.
-黄昏兄弟 -晚上好 德默泽尔
-Brother Dusk. -Good evening, Demerzel.
今天你没去王座室 大帝很想你
Empire missed you in the throne room.
我不这么想
I don't think so.
-你要去哪里  -你很清楚
-Where are you going? -You know where.
天啊
Gods.
那里 在那里降落
There. Put us down there.
觉醒之际
Upon awakening,
愿沉睡者洗净他们眼中曾目睹的邪恶
may the Sleeper cleanse these eyes of the evil they have seen.
-大帝 -大帝 请帮帮我们
-Empire. -Empire, please help us.
武器留在门外
Weapons left outside.
我没带武器
I have no weapon.
任何形式的武器
All of the weapons.
-她什么都没携带 -不是她 是他
-She has nothing. -Not her. Him.
这里不欢迎他的机械
His machines are not welcome here.
大帝
Empire--
隔绝肉身之触摸的人也隔绝了上帝
He who shrouds himself from man's touch shrouds himself from God.
所以我现在被上帝触摸了
And so now am I touched by God?
不 只是我而已
No. Just me.
大帝 这里的结构还不安稳 我们应该回到穿梭机上
Empire, the structures are still settling. We should return to the shuttle.
你的石头 你用它们祈祷
Your stones. You use them to pray.
我们与沉睡者对话 沉睡者能看见我们
We speak to the Sleeper, and the Sleeper sees us.
你们自称先知 是吗 你们能预知未来
You claim to be seers, yes? You know the future.
未来源自沉睡者的梦
The Sleeper dreams our future.
指点过去有什么意义呢
What use would it be to guide our past?
你为什么出席了哈里谢顿的审判
Why were you at Hari Seldon's trial?
你为什么对盖尔多尼克感兴趣
What is your interest in Gaal Dornick?
你为什么在乎她
Why do you care for her?
拥有好奇心不是罪孽
There is no sin in curiosity.
在你的星球上并非如此
There is on your planet.
-大帝 我们必须离开了 -我明白了
-Empire, we must go. -I understand now.
他想知道她是不是真正的先知
He wants to know if she's a true seer.
她是否真的看见了谢顿所说的灭亡
If she truly saw the fall Seldon spoke of.
她的数学计算是否能让她预知灭亡
If her math allowed her to see this.
她来过这里 我知道
She came here. I know she did.
-你们谈论了什么  -大帝
-What did you talk about? -Empire.
-你的上帝把帝国的事告诉她了吗  -沉睡者不认识她
-Did your god tell her about the Empire? -The Sleeper doesn't know her.
-大帝 跟我们走吧 -她不是先知 你的帝国必将灭亡
-Empire. Come with us. -She is not a seer. Your empire is doomed.
最高深的数学就像第六感
The most advanced math is like a sixth sense.
正确的计算能让我们预知未来
The right calculation can allow us to see over the horizon.
如果足够幸运 它能帮助我们 为迎接未来做准备
And if we're lucky, it can help us prepare for what comes next.
86981767
86,981,767.
86981771
86,981,771.
86981779
86,981,779.
你在水下待了很久
You were down there a long time.
是吗
Was I?
我都开始担心你不会出来了
I was beginning to worry that you weren't ever going to come up.
为什么总在黑暗中游
Why always in the dark?
为什么需要光
Why in the light?
黑暗滋生羞愧
Shame grows in darkness.
你没什么需要羞愧的
You've nothing to be ashamed about.
哈里 你想谈什么事吗
Hari, is there something you wanna talk about?
见到你那天 我对瑞驰说
The day I met you, I said to Raych…
“她超出了我的预期”
"She exceeds my expectations."
你们俩都是
You both do.
过去几个月是天赐给我的
You know, these last few months have been a gift.
在流放的事上 我赌了一把
I gambled on exile.
我尽自己所能操控结果 但…
I did my best to engineer the outcome, but…
我从没想过自己也会成为飞船上的一员
I never expected that I would be among the ship's occupants.
是什么变了
What changed?
基地的会议别迟到
Don't be late for the Foundation meeting.
在路易斯皮仁恩眼中 早到五分钟等于迟到三分钟
Five minutes early is three minutes late to Lewis Pirenne.
他知道我们的事了
He knows about us.
他是心理历史学家 他研究的是数学 不是人心
He's a psychohistorian. He reads math, not minds.
我也研究数学 而我很清楚你此刻在想什么
I read math too, and I know exactly what you're thinking.
你不敢告诉他 你不想聊这件事
You're afraid to tell him, and you don't wanna talk about it.
-我们说好了的 -你说他不会认可
-We both agreed. -You told me he wouldn't like it.
-是的 -因为他不希望我们幸福
-He wouldn't. -Because he doesn't want us to be happy?
因为他认为感情令人分心
Because he thinks relationships are a distraction.
如果把人类的感情排除出去 那我们要拯救什么
If we factor out human relationships, what are we trying to save?
他不是说我们必须成为机器人
He's not saying we have to be robots.
-他只是认为你和我… -所以他是嫉妒
-He just thinks that you and I-- -So he's jealous then?
计算过程不完整
The math's not complete.
-什么  -那个计算
-What? -The math.
哈里的计划并没有完全计算好
Hari's Plan. It's not all worked out.
我拿到元光体时看见了 我在审判时没有提这点
I saw it when I had the Prime Radiant. I never mentioned it in the trial.
计划几乎完成了 我不是说它差很多 但它并没有解决一切问题
It's close. I'm not saying it's not close, but not everything is solved.
就像一个一千块的拼图
It's like a puzzle with a thousand pieces.
即使缺失了几块 你依然可以大致看出拼图的全貌
If a few are missing, you know with a high probability what the picture is,
但那几块仍然是缺失的
but they're still missing.
缺失了多少块
How many pieces are missing?
足够拼出不同的一副图吗
Enough to make a different picture?
我不知道 有可能
I don't know. Maybe.
你知道谢顿博士在哪吗
Do you know where Dr. Seldon is?
他不会来了
He's not coming.
-我代他参加 -好吧
-I'm sitting in. -All right.
我们随时可以开始
When you're ready.
马莉 你能说一说
Mari, would you like to bring us up to speed
预算小组委员会目前的进展吗
from the budget subcommittee?
小组委员会确认 将初始研发及测量预算的5.6%
The subcommittee confirms assigning 5.6% of the initial research and survey budget
分配给其中3%最接近川陀的星球
to the 3% of planets closest to Trantor.
5.6%算多吗
Is 5.6% a lot?
似乎很多
It seems like a lot.
不好意思 可以提问吗
I'm sorry. Is it okay to ask questions?
当然
Of course.
但这不是我们第一次讨论
But it's not the first time that we have discussed
从哪里开始着手我们的保护工作
where to begin our preservation work.
分配算法是否偏重异质
Does the allocation algorithm weight towards heterogeny,
如果是 要如何量化
and if so, how is that measured?
多样性和差异性是基地使命的基石
Diversity and variance are cornerstones of the Foundation's mission.
那些内部星系的世界包含四十万亿人口
Those inner worlds represent 40 trillion people,
300个星球、超过100种不同语言
300 planets, over a hundred different languages.
分配方式由我们决定 而不是计算公式
And we decide the allocations, not a computer program.
关键在于 分配方式 是基于基地的价值体系决定的
Point is, the allocations were developed through the Foundation's values.
所以我们保存什么 即反映我们本身的价值观
So what we save says everything about who we are.
当然
Of course.
那么基地对十进制怎么看
And what is the Foundation's feeling about base ten?
-什么意思  -十进制
What do you mean? Base ten.
计数的进位制 一、二、三、四
The numbering system, one, two, three, four--
我们知道那是什么
We know what it is.
你们当然知道
Of course you do,
因为那是川陀的数学系统
because it's the math of Trantor
也是银河3%内部星系中 几乎所有系统采用的数学系统
and the math of almost every single system in the inner 3% of the galaxy.
我猜你们打算保存它
I assume you aim to preserve it?
那是我们计数的方式
It's how we count.
是你计数的方式
It's how you count,
也是你邻居计数的方式
and your neighbors.
你们会保存12进制或27进制吗
Will you be preserving base 12 or 27?
超过一千个世界使用12进制
Over a thousand worlds use base 12
因为能够被12整除的数字比10更多
because 12 is cleanly divisible by more factors than 10 is.
300个恒星系统使用27进制
300 systems use base 27.
这源于数身体的不同部分
It comes from counting body parts.
-你想说什么  -我想说的是
-What is your point? -My point is,
当我们开始保存…
as we begin preserving the most…
文明最重要的部分
essential pieces of civilization,
决定什么将被铭记
deciding what is remembered,
什么将被遗忘
what is forgotten…
我们要如何作出决定
how will we know what those things are
因为我们连在计数方式上都无法达成一致
if we can't even agree on how to count them?
好了
All right.
你确定
Are you sure?
-你看起来仍然… -你毋须担心我
-You still seem-- -You needn't worry about me.
你差点丧命
You could've died.
我已经成功地活了很久
I've managed not to for a long while now.
你知道我和你不同
You know I'm not the same as you.
你的同类都死了
The rest of your kind died.
它们没有死 只是被你的同类所摧毁
They didn't die. They were destroyed by your kind.
这是不同的
It's different.
所以你不喜欢让我看到你真实的样子
Is that why you don't like me to see how you really are?
我不喜欢的原因是这个过程不体面
I don't like it because it's immodest.
-但… -我的行为举止越接近人类
-But-- -The more human I act,
我就越像个人类
the more human I am.
不遵从一种现实生活是会令人迷惑的
It's confusing not to commit to one reality.
你在躲避我
You're avoiding me.
却躲不了
Hardly.
你知道我讨厌楼梯
You know I hate the stairs.
你讨厌的是这个
You hate this.
如果我想因为年老大帝的模样感到感伤
If I want to sentimentalize old emperors,
我只需看餐桌对面的脸就行了
I can just look across the dinner table.
在你这个年纪时我也是这样
-I felt the same way when I was your age.
你能否想象…
Can you imagine…
一个人要有多狂妄自大 才会如此看重自己的能力、头脑
the sheer hubris required to think so much of your abilities, your mind,
以己为尊
so much of your own heart,
以至于你决定从此之后
that you decide from now on,
不仅要当第一 还要当唯一
that not only will you be the first, but the one?
“我将成为所有河流的源头”
"I will be the river from which all rivers flow."
他的想法是对的
He was right.
当然 但看看我们的处境
Of course. And yet here we are.
数百万人丧生 预言称还将有数万亿人死亡
Millions dead, with a prophecy of trillions more.
-谢顿不过是一个人 -就如曾经的我们
-Seldon is just a man. -And so were we once.
你为什么去疤痕区
Why did you go to the Scar?
是为了见祭司吗
Was it to see the priest?
废墟里还埋着尸体
They're still pulling bodies out of the wreckage.
几周都没清理完
As they have been for weeks.
我想看看我们的世界到底发生了什么
I wanted to see what happened to our world,
这是你作为大帝应该做的
as you should have as emperor.
我是大帝 至少在这件事上你是诚实的
I am emperor. At least you're honest about that.
我想和安纳克里昂及狄斯比斯的使团见面
I want to meet with the Anacreon and Thespin delegates.
-这不是你的职责 -对 但这是我的权利
-It's not your job. -No, but it is my right.
这不是个陷阱
It's not a trick.
要下毒的话 我不会用这么好的陈酿
If it were, there are lesser vintages to poison.
敬未来
To the future.
愿它善待我们所有人
May it be kind to all of us.
你想要什么
What do you want?
我只要真相
Only the truth.
几周来我们一直坦诚相待
For weeks now, we have been nothing but honest.
我们为什么要唱一首安纳克里昂歌 然后否认我们做过
Why would we sing an Anacreon song, then deny it was us who had done so?
也许是你们中的极端分子
The extremists amongst your ranks?
你必须承认这说不通
You must admit it makes no sense.
也可能你们的政府对你们有所隐瞒
Or perhaps your government has not told you everything.
我们是帝国忠诚的子民 已经长达三千年
We have been loyal citizens of the Imperium for 3,000 years.
这对安纳克里昂有什么好处
How would this profit Anacreon?
有人试图摧毁我们
Someone is trying to destroy us.
有人想让我们堕入黑暗
Someone is punishing us to darkness.
求求你
Please.
你们会死去
You're going to die.
帝国将处决你们
The Empire is going to kill you,
即使那样也不足以惩罚你们的罪行
and it won't be enough for what you did.
这是为了刺鼻的气味 为了眼睛承受的酸痛
For the smells. For the stinging in the eyes.
为了让我们如鲠在喉的 那些化为灰烬的儿童和父母
The dust of children, mothers and fathers in our throats.
这就是我嘴里的味道
It is a taste in my mouth!
这股味道永不会散去
It is a taste that will not go away.
这是“功业” 你们的和我们的
This is the legacy. Yours and ours.
也许我们希望这不是事实
We may wish it is not.
我们可以大喊这不公平 这的确不公平
We may scream it is not fair, and we would be right.
因为我相信你们
Because I believe you.
你们中的一方说了真话
One of you is telling the truth.
也许两方都说了真话
Maybe even both.
我们应该放你们走
We should let you all go free.
应该这么做
We should.
但我们不会这么做
But we won't.
老头越来越衰弱了 对吧
The old man is declining, isn't he?
谢顿博士
Dr. Seldon.
出什么问题了吗  我们送货时漏了什么吗
Is something wrong? Did we miss something from our delivery?
不是的 我只是想到一件特别的白衬衫
No, no. I was just thinking about a particular white shirt.
袖口有个墨迹
It has an ink stain on the cuff.
我们还没能去除污渍
We haven't been able to remove the stain yet.
其他地方洗干净了吧
Is it clean otherwise?
如果洗干净了就给我吧 有墨迹也没关系
I'd like it if it is. Stain and all.
谢顿博士
Dr. Seldon?
是
Yes?
先生 能问你一个问题吗
Can I ask you a question, sir?
当然 回答问题是我的天职
Of course. I've made a life out of it.
-你满意吗  -满意
-Are you happy? -Happy?
对计划的进展满意吗 准备工作
Happy with the progress of the Plan? The preparations?
你叫什么
What's your name?
维娜
Veena.
维娜阿鲁瓦利亚
Veena Ahluwalia.
这将是一个漫长的旅程 维娜
Well, it's going to be a long journey, Veena.
我们曾经历重重困难 之后还将有更多
We've faced challenges. Many more will follow.
但我坚信我们的努力终将获得成功
But I am confident in the success of our endeavor.
而成功的主要原因是你们
And the principal reason for that is you.
你们每一个人
All of you.
乘客名单是我批准的
I approved the passenger manifest.
上面的每一个名字都是
Each and every name on it.
100年以后
A hundred years from now,
也许是一千年以后 你们的名字将被铭记
perhaps even a thousand, your names will be memorialized.
一群心怀信念的人选择支持一位怪人
The believers who threw their lot in with an eccentric
这位怪人将整个星系的命运 寄托在一个如此抽象的定理上
that pinned the fate of the galaxy on the back of a theorem so abstract,
如此…
well…
说是祷告都不为过
it might as well have been a prayer.
无论你们做了什么
And it won't matter what you did,
无论你曾是超声波清洁人员
whether you worked as an ultrasound scrubber,
热转换工程师还是这个洗衣房的工人
a heat exchange engineer or here in the laundry.
如果没有人 这个祷告就无法延续下去
Because that prayer can't endure without people.
没有你们就不会延续
Without you.
所以…
So…
谢谢你 维娜
thank you, Veena.
墨迹的事很抱歉 先生
I'm sorry about the ink, sir.
没关系 我已经习惯了
No matter. I'm used to it.
这是努力工作的标志
It's a sign of hard work.
谢顿博士
Dr. Seldon?
是 瑟伦
Yes, Theron?
我能握握你的手吗
May I shake your hand?
谢谢
Thank you.
-谢谢你 博士 -谢谢你…
-Thank you, Doctor. -Thank you. Thank you.
谢谢
Thank you.
我只是说他并不是完人
I'm just saying he's not perfect.
阿巴斯 三维打印的度量标准进展如何
Abbas, how are we doing with the 3D-printed metrics?
我们最近在用粘土…
We've been working with clay…
一直在找你
Been looking for you.
你为什么在预算会议上离场  我还想看到一张友善的脸呢
Why'd you leave the budget meeting? Could've used a friendly face.
抱歉 哈里觉得我们 应该计划进行太空行走模拟
Sorry, Hari thinks we should plan to sim a space walk.
现在吗 我们连在雪上走都没把握
Now? We can't even walk on snow.
-我会找他谈的 -不 总之…我会想办法
-I'll talk to him. -No, just-- I'll figure it out.
能帮忙把葡萄酒递给我吗
Can you pass the wine please?
葡萄酒
The wine.
还有位置吗
Is there room?
-有的 当然 -谢谢
-Oh, yes. Of course. -Thank you.
瑞驰 你大概不记得
Raych, you probably don't remember the first meal
我们第一次共同进餐的场景了 是吧
that you and I had together, do you?
是 我不记得了
No, I can't say I do.
那顿饭不丰盛
Well, it wasn't much.
这点我必须承认
I can say that.
那时我刚在大学入职
I'd just started at the university,
餐费津贴不多
didn't have much of a food budget.
我吃的都是不新鲜的酸面包 和放了一天的烤鹰肉
I'd get stale sourdough and day-old roast alley-hawk.
油腻 都是碎骨头
-Greasy, you know, little bones. -Mmm.
不过加热后裹在面包里吃
But warmed up, wrapped in the bread.
人间美味
Was heaven.
他当时六岁 可能七岁
He was six, maybe seven.
被我在稀有书籍室里逮到
I caught him in the rare books room,
他的裤子里藏了两本艾尔华瑞兹对开本
two Alvarez folios stuffed in his pants.
我至今没弄清
I never did figure out,
你是怎么知道艾尔华瑞兹的作品 在黑市上的卖价最高
how did you know Alvarez would bring you the most money on the black market
同时又最容易塞进短裤里
whilst also being the easiest to shove in your shorts?
你的母亲已经过世 至少根据我的解读是如此
Your mother, as far as I could decipher, had passed,
你的父亲把你带回家的钱都换成酒喝了
and your father was drinking whatever money you were able to bring back.
不是的
That's wrong.
我的父亲没有喝酒
My father wasn't drinking.
他有喝酒 孩子
He was, son.
我父亲在热沉室工作
My father worked in the heat sinks.
他出了意外 他的背部被烧伤
He'd been in an accident. He had a burn down his back.
我偷书是为了买药
I stole the books for medicine,
好让他回去上班
so he could go back to work.
他是之后才开始喝酒的
He didn't drink until later.
在我离开家与你一起生活之后
After I left to live with you.
我显然更擅长预测未来
Apparently, I'm better at predicting the future
而不是回忆过去
than I am at remembering the past.
嘿
Hey.
我从没见过这个场景模式
I've never seen that setup before.
每两年才会出现一次
It only happens once every two years,
所以他们在模拟时不用这个场景
so they never use it for the sim.
你和哈里是怎么了
What's happening with you and Hari?
没什么
Nothing.
Nothing?
没什么
Nothing.
也许我不该把我做的事告诉你
Maybe I shouldn't have told you what I did…
关于数学计算那件事
about the math.
不 那…刚好提醒了我
No, it was a… good reminder.
哈里也会犯错 他不是完人
Hari makes mistakes. He's not perfect.
对 我只是怕我不知道哪些错误是要紧的
Yeah, I'm just afraid I don't know which mistakes are important.
缺失了一些拼图块也没关系 并不会改变全景
Which puzzle pieces can be missing and it still be the right picture.
但你仍然相信计算结果
But you still believe in the math.
我相信
I do.
这是计划
This is the Plan.
我们现在不能回头
We're not turning around now.
但我仍觉得他是嫉妒
I still think he's jealous though.
是 谁不会嫉妒
Yeah. Who wouldn't be?
到端点星之后我们就更自由了
When we get to Terminus, we'll have more freedom.
属于我们的冰雪小天地
Our own little piece of frigid land.
我们会建造一个家
We'll build a home.
也许还有几个孩子在炉火边小睡
Maybe with a couple kids dozing by the fire?
提起孩子 你就陷入了如此凝重的沉默
That's a pretty loaded silence after mentioning kids.
你还想要孩子吗
Still want them?
盖尔
Gaal…
和你一起
with you…
我想要一切
I want it all.
美好时光果然短暂
That was nice while it lasted.
等等
Hold on.
星桥
The Star Bridge.
关于安纳克里昂和狄斯比斯 我们必须得出一个结论
We need to come to a conclusion about Anacreon and Thespis.
你明白我的想法
You know how I feel.
我认为帝国能承担恩赦的后果
I think the Empire can withstand a bout of grace.
甚至可能从中获得好处
Maybe even benefit.
很难相信你还是那个
It's hard to believe you're the same man
在谈论哈里谢顿的事情时说
whose advice on all things Hari Seldon was,
“在动用武力上不用顾虑太多”的人
"Do not overthink the stick."
我还是那个人
I am the same man as that.
我和你也是同一种人
As I am the same man as you.
初升的黎明 你如何看此事
What do you think, Ascending Dawn?
我们被袭击 你有什么感觉
We've been attacked. How does that make you feel?
说吧 年轻人
Go ahead, young man.
回答他
You answer him.
-我感到害怕 -是
-I'm scared. -Yes.
没错 这是人之常情 害怕
That's right. That's what people are. Scared.
所以现在我们在表面上最应该展现的…
Which is why the best face we can project outward now…
是力量
is one of strength.
帝王的和平
The Emperor's peace.
是帝国的承诺
It is the promise of the Imperium.
这是克里昂一世和 他之后每一位克里昂的承诺
It was the promise of Cleon I and each Cleon after him.
这是一项跨越世纪的竞赛
It is a race run across centuries,
代代相传的火炬
a baton handed from generation to generation.
我们不会丢掉火炬
And we will not drop it.
今天不会 明天不会 以后都不会
Not today or tomorrow or any tomorrow after.
威胁和平 就要付出沉重代价
Threaten the peace and pay a dear price.
川陀受了重创
Trantor has been deeply wounded.
没有民众幸免
None of our citizens remain untouched.
我们的痛苦将波及后世
The pain will be felt by all for generations.
这将给他们留下永不褪去的伤痕 但他们将存活下去
It will scar them forever, but they will survive.
民众的生活将继续 我们的世界将继续
They will live on. Our world will live on!
你们…
You…
则死路一条
will not.
你们的世界也死路一条
And neither will your worlds.
至少别想不留伤口和疤痕
Not without wounds and scars!
看好了
Look.
回到你们的世界
Go back to your worlds.
告诉在世和亡故的人 你们未能拯救他们
Tell the living and the dead you failed to save them.
并非每一次抉择都像今天这样
Not every choice will be like this one.
但有时会是这样
But sometimes?
有时会是这样
Sometimes.
你不会孤军作战
You won't be alone.
你的兄弟和我会陪着你
You'll have your brothers and me.
我会一直陪在你身边 就如一直以来那样
I'll always be here, as I always have been.
结局常常是这样吗
How often does it end like this?
我们有多常会做出这样的选择
How often do we choose this?
你每一次都做出这样的选择
You always do.
传统的力量保护着我们
The weight of traditions protects us.
跟随前人的脚步前进能让人感到一种心安
There can be comfort in making a journey others have made before.
曾几何时 我用父母的话祷告
Once, I prayed in the words of my parents.
后来 我的世界扩张了 那些话已无法描绘我的现实
But then my world expanded, and the words fell short of my reality.
如今我用另一种语言祷告
I pray in a different language now.
86981803
86,981,803.
86981821
86,981,821.
86981827
86,981,827.
86981848
86,981,848.
不 这不对
No. Not right.
86981849
86,981,849.
一定是出了什么问题
Something's wrong.
瑞驰
Raych?
瑞驰 你做了…
Raych, what are you--
盖尔 你必须离开这里
Gaal, you have to leave.
-你做了什么  -你不能留在这里
-What have you done? -You can't be here.
-盖尔… -哈里
-Gaal. Gaal. -Hari.
哈里
Hari.
哈里…
Hari. Hari.
盖尔 你必须离开 现在就走 盖尔
Gaal, you have to leave. Now! Gaal!
警告…
Warning. Warning.
哈里谢顿生命机能已停止
Designate Hari Seldon's life functions have ceased.
警告…
Warning. Warning.
盖尔、瑞驰
Gaal? Raych?
-快走… -怎么回事
-Come on! Come on! -What's going on?
警告 哈里谢顿生命机能已停止
Warning. Designate Hari Seldon's life functions have ceased.
警告…
Warning. Warning.
哈里谢顿生命机能已停止
Designate Hari Seldon's life functions have ceased.
-天啊 -进去
-Oh, my God. -Get in.
别惊慌 你不会有事的
Don't panic. You're gonna be okay.
别反抗…
Don't fight it. Don't fight it.
保持冷静 你可以呼吸的…
Keep calm. You can breathe. You can breathe.
你可以在液体中呼吸 保持冷静
You can breathe the fluid. Keep calm.
记住数质数…
Remember to count primes. Remember to count primes.
记住数质数
Remember to count primes.
我爱你
I love you.
对不起
I'm sorry.
86981861
86,981,861.
86981893
86,981,893.
86981897
86,981,897.
86981927
86,981,927.
和你一起 我想要一切
With you, I want it all.
…981953
…981,953.
86981…
Eighty-six million, nine hundred and eighty-one thousand…
字幕翻译：易晗